Guide to the Printmaker File [1730]-2014, undated (bulk 1800-1860) PR 58
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Prints 16 x 20" to 30 x 40", 111340
  Pierre Charles Canot, a French engraver working in London, engraved these two views of New York City after drawings by Thomas Howdell, a member of the Royal Artillery of the British Army. They were published in London in around 1768 as part of Scenographia America, a collection of twenty-eight views of American cities. The view from the south-east includes one of the first impressions of King's College (now Columbia University).
  Amos Doolittle's son A. B. Doolittle's engraving of Yale College is included in this series.
  The French lithographing firm of Engelmann Pére et Fils (Godefroy Engelmann, principal) completed six scenes of Vues de L'Amerique du Nord; all six were printed as the basis for wallpaper blocks. Complete sets are rare; the Society has three. The view of New York includes African Americans.
  The etching by Paul Fourdrinier is the earliest plan of Savannah known to exist. The first settlers came in 1733, and the print was issued the next year.
  Ambroise-Louis Garneray, a French artist and engraver, issued a series of travel views in the early eighteenth century, Vues des coites de France dans l'Ocean et dans la Mediteranee. The fifth volume, Voyage Maritime, featured views of great port cities, including several American ports. Garneray never visited America but copied the views of other artists.
  Thomas Johnston's view of the battle at Lake George is from the French and Indian War.
  Paul Sandby 1725-1809 is considered the founder of the watercolor movement in England, and was also the first English artist to use the aquatint process. The views by and after Sandby here were originally sketches by the colonial Massachusetts Governor Thomas Pownall. Sandby painted each view, and engraved several of them. The six prints here were first published in 1761 under the title of Six Remarkable Views in the Provinces of New-York, New-Jersey, and Pennsylvania, in North America, and were later reissued as part of Scenographia Americana, mentioned above, in 1768.
  Prints are filed alphabetically by artist or printmaker's surname.
  - Akrell, Carl Frederik (1779-1868), 111467
    After Axel Leonhard Klinckowstrom (1775-1837).
    - "Broadway -Gatan Och Radhuset I New York" [Broadway and City Hall], 1819; 111471 (Box Unknown container 832 for instance of "Broadway -Gatan Och Radhuset I New York" [Broadway and City Hall], Folder unknown container)
    - "New Yorks Hamn Och Redd Fran Brooklyn Pa Long Island" [New York Harbor from Brooklyn], 1820; 111470 (Box Unknown container 833 for instance of "New Yorks Hamn Och Redd Fran Brooklyn Pa Long Island" [New York Harbor from Brooklyn], Folder unknown container)
      aquatint, 2 copies
    - "Chancellor Livingston", [1819]; 111469 (Box Unknown container 834 for instance of "Chancellor Livingston", Folder unknown container)
      plan of boat
    - "Atlas" title page, 1824; 111468 (Box Unknown container 835 for instance of "Atlas" title page, Folder unknown container)
  - Barlow, Lou (1908-2011), 111460
    - "Cafe", linocut, artist's proof, ca. 1935; 111466 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "Dialogue," color linocut, impression 7 of 14, 1990; 111465 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "The Rescue", color linocut, artist's proof, ca.1991; 111464 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "The Sculptor", linocut, artist's proof, 1994; 111463 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "Self Portrait", linocut, artist's proof, 2003; 111462 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "Symphony Orchestra", linocut, artist's proof, 1988; 111461 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Beamley, William Jean, 20590
    - Chambers Street, New York City, 1913; 20591 (Box Unknown container 836 for instance of Chambers Street, New York City, Folder unknown container)
      Photomechanical reproduction, color
  - Behnken, William (b.1943), 20588
    - Bronx Crossing, 1991; 20589 (Box Unknown container 837 for instance of Bronx Crossing, Folder unknown container)
  - Bosman, Richard (b. 1944), 112049
    - [Brooklyn Bridge], undated; 112051 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Briem, Gottlob L. (1899-1972), 20586
    - The Chrysler Building, New York City, N.Y., undated; 20587 (Box Unknown container 838 for instance of The Chrysler Building, New York City, N.Y., Folder unknown container)
  - Brosen, Frederick (b. 1954), 112050
    - [Brooklyn Bridge], 1992; 112052 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Brown, Goerge Loring (1814-1889), 111458
    - [New York City from across river], 1861; 111459 (Box Unknown container 839 for instance of [New York City from across river], Folder unknown container)
      Finished by Alexander Hay Ritchie (1822-1895). Published by George Ward Nichols, New York
  - Bry, Edith (1898-1991), 111456
    - "Sold", undated; 111457 (Box Unknown container 840 for instance of "Sold", Folder unknown container)
      lithograph, impression 9 of 20
      See also: Series I
  - Canot, Pierre-Charles (1710-1777), 111453
    after Thomas Howdell.
    - "A South East View of the City of New York in North America", [1768]; 111455 (Box Unknown container 841 for instance of "A South East View of the City of New York in North America", Folder unknown container)
      published by T. Jefferys, London
    - "A South West View of the City of New York in North America", [1768]; 111454 (Box Unknown container 842 for instance of "A South West View of the City of New York in North America", Folder unknown container)
  - Cartwright, T., 111451
    After a drawing by George Beck (ca. 1748-1812).
    - "East View of Baltimore, Maryland", 1802; 111452 (Box Unknown container 843 for instance of "East View of Baltimore, Maryland", Folder unknown container)
      colored aquatint, published by Atkins & Nightingale, London & Philadelphia
  - Cohen, Arthur Allen (b. 1928), 20581
    - Brooklyn Bridge 1 (artist's proof), [1982]; 20585 (Box Unknown container 844 for instance of Brooklyn Bridge 1 (artist's proof), Folder unknown container)
    - Brooklyn Bridge 2 (artist's proof), [1982]; 20584 (Box Unknown container 845 for instance of Brooklyn Bridge 2 (artist's proof), Folder unknown container)
    - Brooklyn Bridge 9 (artist's proof), 1982; 20583 (Box Unknown container 846 for instance of Brooklyn Bridge 9 (artist's proof), Folder unknown container)
    - Brooklyn Bridge 9 (artist's proof), [1982]; 20582 (Box Unknown container 847 for instance of Brooklyn Bridge 9 (artist's proof), Folder unknown container)
  - Connell, Edwin V.D. (b. 1859), 20579
    - [From the Tower of the Produce Exchange], with remarques of Produce Exchange Tower and Statue of Liberty], 1889; 20580 (Box Unknown container 848 for instance of [From the Tower of the Produce Exchange], with remarques of Produce Exchange Tower and Statue of Liberty], Folder unknown container)
  - Dawes, D.B. (?), 111449
    - [Village church], undated; 111450 (Box Unknown container 849 for instance of [Village church], Folder unknown container)
  - Doolittle, Amos (1754-1832), 111447
    - "A New Display of the United States", 1803; 111448 (Box Unknown container 850 for instance of "A New Display of the United States", Folder unknown container)
      printed and sold by Doolittle, New Haven
  - Doolittle, A. B., 111445
    - "A View of the Buildings of Yale College at New Haven", 1807; 111446 (Box Unknown container 851 for instance of "A View of the Buildings of Yale College at New Haven", Folder unknown container)
      published by A. Doolittle & Son, New Haven
  - Edy, John William (fl. 1780-1820), 111443
    after George Bulteel Fisher (1764-after 1796).
    - "View of St. Anthony's Nose, on the North River Province of New York", 1795; 111444 (Box Unknown container 852 for instance of "View of St. Anthony's Nose, on the North River Province of New York", Folder unknown container)
      aquatint, published by Edy, Westminster
  - Engelmann, Pére et Fils, 111440
    - "Vues de l'Amerique du Nord (1r au 10e le)" [Niagara/Vue de New-York/West Point], [1825-1830]; 111442 (Box Unknown container 853 for instance of "Vues de l'Amerique du Nord (1r au 10e le)" [Niagara/Vue de New-York/West Point], Folder unknown container)
    - "Vues de l'Amerique du Nord (23me au 32me le)" [Jeux Indiens/Pont de Virginie/Les chutes de Niagara], [1825-1830]; 111441 (Box Unknown container 854 for instance of "Vues de l'Amerique du Nord (23me au 32me le)" [Jeux Indiens/Pont de Virginie/Les chutes de Niagara], Folder unknown container)
  - Etwiller, ?, 111438
    - [Toll Bridge], 1926; 111439 (Box Unknown container 855 for instance of [Toll Bridge], Folder unknown container)
  - Ferguson, Max (b. 1959), 20577
    - [Waiting at the Spring Street Station (55/75), 1985; 20578 (Box Unknown container 856 for instance of [Waiting at the Spring Street Station (55/75), Folder unknown container)
  - Fiene, Ernest (1894-1965), 20574
    - Waterfront, Manhattan (3/100), 1931; 20575 (Box Unknown container 857 for instance of Waterfront, Manhattan (3/100), Folder unknown container)
    - Waterfront, Manhattan (89/100), 1931; 20886 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
      Provenance
      Gift of Pam Schaffler
    - New York Skyline(21/40), 1932; 20887 (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - New York Skyline (26/40), 1932; 20576 (Box Unknown container 858 for instance of New York Skyline (26/40), Folder unknown container)
  - Fourdrinier, Paul (fl. 1720-2760), 111436
    after Peter Gordon
    - "A View of Savanah as it stood the 29th of March 1734", 111437 (Box Unknown container 859 for instance of "A View of Savanah as it stood the 29th of March 1734", Folder unknown container)
      etching, two copies, both colored
  - Garneray, Ambroise-Louis (1783-1857), 111433
    - "A View of New-York, taken from Veahawk", 1834; 111435 (Box Unknown container 860 for instance of "A View of New-York, taken from Veahawk", Folder unknown container)
      aquatint by Sigismond Himely, 1801-1872, after a painting by Garneray, Published by Basset, Paris
    - "Vue du Port de Baltimore", [1843-1844]; 111434 (Box Unknown container 861 for instance of "Vue du Port de Baltimore", Folder unknown container)
      aquatint after his own design, published by Hocquart, Paris, and by Bailly, Ward & Co., New York
  - Golinkin, Joseph Webster (1897-1977), 20569
    - Black Window, ca. 1928; 20573 (Box Unknown container 862 for instance of Black Window, Folder unknown container)
    - [National Horse Show at Madison Square Garden], ca. 1938; 20572 (Box Unknown container 863 for instance of [National Horse Show at Madison Square Garden], Folder unknown container)
    - [Park Avenue; view south toward New York Central Building] (13/50), [1935]; 20571 (Box Unknown container 864 for instance of [Park Avenue; view south toward New York Central Building] (13/50), Folder unknown container)
    - [Speakeasy interior] (7/24), [1928]; 20570 (Box Unknown container 865 for instance of [Speakeasy interior] (7/24), Folder unknown container)
  - Graham, George (fl. 1786-1813), 111431
    after Archibald Robertson (1765-1835).
    - "A View on Hudson River, taken from the farm of Mr. James Renwick upon Chambers Creek near Newburgh", 1795; 111432 (Box -, Folder unknown container)
      mezzotint stipple engraving, published by James Harrison, New York
  - Grooms, Red (b. 1937), 114591 (Box-folder .)
    - Lunchtime on Broadway, 2009; 114592 (Box -, Folder unknown container)
      Etching with aquatint, spitbite aquatint and scrapping
  - Hagopian, Vahan (b. 1889), 20565
    - [51st St. and Park Ave., showing St. Bartholmew's Church], undated; 20568 (Box Unknown container 866 for instance of [51st St. and Park Ave., showing St. Bartholmew's Church], Folder unknown container)
    - Martin Beck Theatre, undated; 20567 (Box Unknown container 867 for instance of Martin Beck Theatre, Folder unknown container)
      lithograph, 2 copies
    - [Street Corner in Midtown], 20566 (Box Unknown container 868 for instance of [Street Corner in Midtown], Folder unknown container)
  - Hall, John (1739-1797), 111429
    after Benjamin West (1738-1820).
    - "William Penn's Treaty with the Indians, when he founded the province of Pennsylvania in North America, 1681", 1775; 111430 (Box Unknown container 869 for instance of "William Penn's Treaty with the Indians, when he founded the province of Pennsylvania in North America, 1681", Folder unknown container)
      engraving, published by John Boydell, London, two copies, one colored
  - Hass, Richard (b. 1936), 111426
    - "View of Woolworth Building from World Trade Center" (30/75), undated; 111428 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "Manhattan View, Twilight", 1999; 111427 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
      Studio proof
  - Hauben, Daniel (b. 1956), 20562
    - Evening Rain (46/50), 1998; 20564 (Box Unknown container 870 for instance of Evening Rain (46/50), Folder unknown container)
    - Fire Escapes (17/35), 1983; 20563 (Box Unknown container 871 for instance of Fire Escapes (17/35), Folder unknown container)
      serigraph
  - Hios, Theo (1908-1999), 20559
    - Brooklyn Bridge Workers, 1937; 20561 (Box Unknown container 872 for instance of Brooklyn Bridge Workers, Folder unknown container)
    - War Victim, 1938; 20560 (Box Unknown container 873 for instance of War Victim, Folder unknown container)
  - Hirschfeld, Al (1903-2003), 111420
    - "1776", 1997; 111425 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
      Brent Spinner, Pat Hingle, Paul Michael Valley, designed by Tony Walton, 1997, AP #VII/XV. Lithograph 20 x 24 in.
    - "A&E Biography (TV)", 1997; 111424 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
      Lithograph 20 x24 in. Historic figures Pres. Ronald Reagan, Gov. Nelson Rockefeller, Marilyn Monroe, Leonardo da Vinci, Mohammad Ali, General George Patton, F. Scott Fitzgerald, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, AP #V/XL
    - "Josephine Baker", 2002; 111423 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
      lithograph, ink and watercolor, 20 x 24, AP #7/40
    - "Cultural Calendar", 1984; 111422 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
      lithograph, 20 x 24 in., Mehta, Bernstein, Tandy, Landsbury, AP #XIII/XXXVIII
    - [Barbara Streisand], undated; 111421 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Hulett, James (d. 1771), 111418
    after Nicholas Garrison.
    - "A View of the House of Employment, Alms-House, Pennsylvania Hospital, & part of the City of Philadelphia", 1787; 111419 (Box Unknown container 874 for instance of "A View of the House of Employment, Alms-House, Pennsylvania Hospital, & part of the City of Philadelphia", Folder unknown container)
      engraving, published by J. Harris, New York, State II
  - Hung, Su-Li (b. 1947), 20556
    - Broken City (6/50), 2001; 20558 (Box Unknown container 875 for instance of Broken City (6/50), Folder unknown container)
    - World Trade Center (2/50), 2001; 20557 (Box Unknown container 876 for instance of World Trade Center (2/50), Folder unknown container)
  - Hunter, F[rederick] Leo (1862-1943), 20553
    - Coenties Slip, South Street, 1881; 20555 (Box Unknown container 877 for instance of Coenties Slip, South Street, Folder unknown container)
    - N.Y. Produce Exchange, 1887; 20554 (Box Unknown container 878 for instance of N.Y. Produce Exchange, Folder unknown container)
  - Jefferys, Thomas, 111416
    After George Heap.
    - "An East Prospect of the City of Philadelphia taken by George Heap from the Jersey Shore", [1756]; 111417 (Box Unknown container 879 for instance of "An East Prospect of the City of Philadelphia taken by George Heap from the Jersey Shore", Folder unknown container)
      engraving, published by Jefferys, London
  - Johnston, Thomas (1708-1767), 111414
    - "A Prospective Plan of the Battle Fought near Lake George on the 8th of Sept. 1755...", 111415 (Box Unknown container 880 for instance of "A Prospective Plan of the Battle Fought near Lake George on the 8th of Sept. 1755...", Folder unknown container)
      after S. Blodget
  - Jukes, Francis (1745-1812), 111410
    after Alexander Robertson (1772-1841).
    - "Hudsons River from Chambers Creek looking thro' the High Lands", 1802; 111413 (Box Unknown container 881 for instance of "Hudsons River from Chambers Creek looking thro' the High Lands", Folder unknown container)
      colored aquatint, published by Jukes, London, and Robertson, New York
    - "New York from Hobuck Ferry House New Jersey", 1800; 111412 (Box Unknown container 882 for instance of "New York from Hobuck Ferry House New Jersey", Folder unknown container)
    - "Mount Vernon in Virginia the Seat of the late Lieut. General George Washington Commander in Chief of the Armies of the United States", 1800; 111411 (Box Unknown container 883 for instance of "Mount Vernon in Virginia the Seat of the late Lieut. General George Washington Commander in Chief of the Armies of the United States", Folder unknown container)
  - Katz, Steven, 83916
    - 57th Street Bridge, 2013; 83917 (Box FF, Folder unknown container)
      General
      Etching
    - Ansonia 1, 2013; 83918 (Box FF, Folder unknown container)
    - Comfort Inn, 2014; 83919 (Box FF, Folder unknown container)
  - Klein, Sabina, 112053
    - Chelsea Afternoon, undated; 112054 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Le Breton, Louis (1818-1866), 111614
    - "Vue de New York Arrivee du transatlantique", 1820; 111615 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Luccio, Marco (b. 1969), 111406
    - "Chinatown" (24/25), 2008; 111409 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "Cranes on 29th Street" (10/25), 2008; 111408 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - "Lights, Cars and the Flatiron" (10/25), 2008; 111407 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Mackay, Donald A., 20551
    - Farewell to the Hotel Astor (35/100), undated; 20552 (Box Unknown container 884 for instance of Farewell to the Hotel Astor (35/100), Folder unknown container)
  - McKenzie, Mary Beth (b. 1946), 200630
    - "Readings by Miss Lil," monotype, 11 1/4" x 14", 2002; 200631 (Folder FF)
    - "Fulton Fish Market," monotype, 12" x 13 1/4", 2002; 200632 (Folder FF)
    - Untitled, monotype, sheet: 12 ½" x 15 9/16", 1999; 200633 (Folder FF)
    - "The Bakery Interior," monotype, 14 7/8" x 12 7/8", 1998; 200634 (Folder FF)
    - Untitled (from the Circus series), monotype, 13 5/8" x 16 ½", 2013; 200635 (Folder FF)
    - "Men at Tire Shop on West 45th Street," monotype, sheet: 14 1/8 x 21", 2013; 200636 (Folder FF)
    - "New York City Horse and Carriage Barn," monotype, sheet: 12 5/8 x 15 7/8 in., ca. 1980; 214250 (Folder FF)
  - Mielatz, Charles Frederick William (1864-1919), 20549
    - The Dewey Arch, 1900; 20550 (Box Unknown container 885 for instance of The Dewey Arch, Folder unknown container)
  - New York Etcher's Press, 111404
    - "A Day in Times Square", 2009; 111405 (Box Flat files, Folder 1)
      Porfolio of nine prints featuring un-edited artist reflectings about Times Square: Arisman, Marshall, "The Dancing Bear" (etching); Chernow, Ann, "Victory Theatre, 1942" (photo-etching); Hardin, Maya, untitled (4-plate, 4-color aquatint); Lasansky, Richie, untitled (engraving, etching, scraped, aquatint, drypoint); Netter, Lou, "Broken Bodies Broken Wallets" (etching, aquatint); Ronalds, Bill, "X-Termination" (aquatint); Waldman, Bruce, untitled (litho crayon open bite).
  - Pantell, Richard (b. 1927), 20547
    - The Five Points, 1985; 20548 (Box Unknown container 886 for instance of The Five Points, Folder unknown container)
  - Pelletieri, Michael (b. 1947), 20738
    - City Signs, 2003; 20739 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Pennell, Joseph (1860-1926), 111402
    - "The Cut Toward Culebra", 1912; 111403 (Box Unknown container 887 for instance of "The Cut Toward Culebra", Folder unknown container)
  - Penney, James (1910-1982), 20545
    - Subway (3/10), 1932; 20546 (Box Unknown container 888 for instance of Subway (3/10), Folder unknown container)
  - Podwal, Mark (b. 1945), 111400
    - "Ship of State", 2002; 111401 (Box Unknown container 889 for instance of "Ship of State", Folder unknown container)
      etching, impression 13 of 60
  - Robinson, Boardman (1856-1952), 112057
    - [Walt Whitman], undated; 112058 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Rollinson, William (1762-1842), 111391
    after John Wood (b. 1775)
    - "New York from Long Island", 1801; 111392 (Box Unknown container 890 for instance of "New York from Long Island", Folder unknown container)
      aquatint, published by Wood and Rollinson, New York
  - Rowland, Susan, 111389
    - "Trinity Graveyard, May 7, 2002", 111390 (Box FF, Folder unknown container)
      Monoprint with weed, 8 x 22 in., signed SR 1/1. Gift of Kate Ganz, 2003.
  - Sakuyama, Shunji, 20540
    - [100 Garfield Place, Brooklyn], 1982; 20544 (Box Unknown container 891 for instance of [100 Garfield Place, Brooklyn], Folder unknown container)
      color lithograph, monoprint
    - [465 Fourteenth Street, Brooklyn] (18/26), 1981; 20543 (Box Unknown container 892 for instance of [465 Fourteenth Street, Brooklyn] (18/26), Folder unknown container)
      color lithograph
    - [558 Second Street, Brooklyn] (12/18), 1983; 20542 (Box Unknown container 893 for instance of [558 Second Street, Brooklyn] (12/18), Folder unknown container)
    - [Room interior] (14/23), 1982; 20541 (Box Unknown container 894 for instance of [Room interior] (14/23), Folder unknown container)
  - Sanchez, Emilio (1921-1999), 73455
    - Crosstown Sunset, color lithograph (47/75), 1976; 73456 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - Crosstown Traffic, color lithograph (4/100), 1998; 73457 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - Hudson River View, color lithograph (8/50), 1980's; 73458 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - Loft Windows, color lithograph (42/100), 1988; 73459 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - Looking West from My Studio, color lithograph (16/100), 1988; 73460 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - New York on a Sunny Day, color lithograph, 73461 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - Nueva York, color lithograph (32/75), ca 1977; 73462 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - The Shadow of the Brooklyn Bridge, color lithograph, (32/100), 1988; 73463 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
    - The View from New York, color lithograph, (1/75), 1976; 73464 (Box Flat files, Folder unknown container)
  - Sandby, Paul (1731-1809), 111381
    after sketches by Thomas Pownall.
    - Title page, "Six Remarkable Views in the Provinces of New-York, New-Jersey, and Pennsylvania, in North America", 1761; 111388 (Box Unknown container 895 for instance of Title page, "Six Remarkable Views in the Provinces of New-York, New-Jersey, and Pennsylvania, in North America", Folder unknown container)
      printed by Thomas Jefferys, London [includes list of 6 plates]
    - "A View in Hudson's River of the Entrance of What is called the Topan Sea", 1761; 111387 (Box Unknown container 896 for instance of "A View in Hudson's River of the Entrance of What is called the Topan Sea", Folder unknown container)
      painted by Sandby, engraved by Peter Benazech, published by Thomas Jefferys, London. Additional copy of a later issue, colored.
    - "A View of the Falls on the Passaick, or Second River, in the Province of New Jersey", 1761; 111386 (Box Unknown container 897 for instance of "A View of the Falls on the Passaick, or Second River, in the Province of New Jersey", Folder unknown container)
      painted and engraved by Sandby, published by Thomas Jefferys, London. Additional copy of a later issue.